Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
Boy, what's this lady
about, why is she so grumpy?
Okay, we're going to talk
about that. Here we go.
SKYE DKA' BA RNAMS LA
DMIGS SU BKAR TE BSGOM
SKYE DKA' BA means difficult to generate
and guess what it means, you guys?
That lady?
What are we on?
We're on compassion.
[TL] Generate responsibility.
[GMR] Well, we didn't reach
quite there yet, but okay.
So if there's people in your life
that you have a lot of trouble
feeling empathy with them.
They are just so irritating that, look,
I know you're suffering
but I don't really care
because you're so irritating.
So if there's difficult
people in your life
to feel empathy with, then DMIGS SU BKAR.
DMIGS SU BKAR is an
idiom, difficult idiom.
BKAR has many different meanings,
but DMIGS SU BKAR means take
them as a separate focus group.
Take all the assholes in your life
and take them as a separate focus group
and focus on them.
DMIGS SU BKAR BA means separate
them out from your life,
all the difficult people,
put them in a special group
and try to get empathy for them.
Work on your empathy for them.
TSANGS PA SOGS LA SKYE DKA' NA
SKYES BU 'BRING GI SKABS
LTAR BSAMS PAS SKYE BA 'ONG
TSANGS PA SOGS here means
Brahma, like worldly god,
like Superman, or Iron
Man, or Wonder Woman.
But the point is, if
there are powerful people,
like powerful politicians,
who you have difficulty
feeling compassion for them
because they are so unkind
or they are so crude people.
And if you feel difficulty, SKYE DKA' NA,
if you have difficulty
feeling empathy for them
then go back to the lower
sections of the Lam Rim,
medium capacity people. Think about, look,
they're also in a body,
their body also hurts,
they also have relationship problems,
they also have financial problems.
Half the rich people in the
world are broke, trust me.
They are just living on huge
debts and they're nervous
and they have family problems.
They have health problems.
They definitely have
mental health problems.
And try to have some empathy
for those difficult people
in your life.
You have trouble feeling
compassion for them,
try to go back to the medium
Lam Rim and think about
the sufferings that we were
supposed to think about
for ourselves and apply
it to those people.
SNYING RJE CHEN PO RGYUD
LA SKYES PA'I TSAD NI
This TSAD has been very
useful throughout this section
of the Lam Rim in the seven step process
for reaching bodhichitta
or bodhisattva's vision.
What's TSAD Tim?
Yeah, how do you know when you got it?
And that's so useful, like how do you know
when you reach compassion,
and you can go on to put responsibility?
How do you know when
you reach number five?
And because it's so difficult
to quantify emotions,
it's so difficult to say,
"Okay, Tim, now you got love,
you didn't have love yesterday
and today you have it."
It's so difficult to put a number on it.
So how do you put a number
on compassion? TSAD NI,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD SDUG BSNGAL
DANG BRAL 'DOD AA MAS BU
GCES PA NAD DRAG PO LTA BU'I SDUG BSNGAL
CAN ZHIG LA SEMS PA BZHIN
When you have this emotion,
like a mother trying to eat
breakfast, while her child
is in the hospital recovering
from a car accident
in which they were almost killed.
So imagine you're a mom.
Here's a picture.
You're a mom, your kid
got in a car accident.
The kid is in the hospital
fighting for their life, and
you're having breakfast. You're
sitting there having coffee.
By the way, she looks too happy.
I'm sorry, I should have found a more...
Anyway, this lady's only
child got almost killed
in a car accident and the
child's in the hospital
struggling for her life or his life,
and then she's having coffee.
But what is she really doing?
She's only thinking about the child.
Her mind is totally
obsessed with the child.
Okay, she has to eat. She has to drink.
She does, parents of kids who are dying
still have breakfast, but during breakfast
you can bet they are not
thinking about breakfast.
So when you reach this point,
BZA' BTUNG GI TSE TSUN CHAD
BZA' BTUNG means while
you're eating your breakfast,
food and drink, and you're still
having thoughts of empathy
about all the other people
in the world having the same
problems at the same moment.
When you reach that point
then you have compassion.
When you can't even during breakfast,
you can't eat a croissant
without being a little bit
distracted about all the
people dying this morning,
then you have compassion.
Then you got it.
As much as a mom would
have for her only child
who's in the hospital
struggling for their life
at that moment. And that,
boy, that's a high bar.
That's a really high bar.
That's a high TSAD.
All right.
DE YANG SDUG BSNGAL LAS BRAL
'DOD TZAM GYI SNYING RJE NI,
NYAN RANG DANG THUN MONG
BA'I SNYING RJE YIN LA
Now he's going to talk about
two kinds of compassion
and two kinds of love.
Okay, we were just struggling
with what's the difference
between love and compassion.
Basically, love is the desire
that people have happiness,
and compassion is the desire
that people don't have suffering,
and there's a debate about
which one should come first.
And to help us with that
debate, Pabongka Rinpoche
is going to split love into two types
and he's going to split
compassion into two types.
And this is not one of
those Gelugpa Tsongkapian,
oh, they just like to make divisions
and more outlines.
It's not really that.
It's that the more subtleties
you learn about compassion,
the easier it will be
for you to develop it.
If you learn several colors of compassion
then you will be better
able to master compassion.
So we're going to talk about
two kinds of compassion here.
First one is SDUG BSNGAL LAS
BRAL 'DOD GYI SNYING RJE,
which means
you want to pull people out of the fire.
People fell in the fire
and you're obsessed
with getting them out of the fire.
You're obsessed with pulling
them out of suffering.
That's the first one.
The second flavor of compassion is...
and oh by the way he says,
"Non-bodhisattvas do have this
first kind of compassion."
So people who didn't reach
bodhisattva vision yet,
like lower track people,
self-made buddhas and listeners,
they still have this
motivation that they don't like
to see people suffering.
That's part of all Buddhist practice.
You don't have to be a bodhisattva
to be concerned about
other people's suffering.
But the second one, SDUG
BSNGAL LAS SKYOB 'DOD,
by the way, heavy prenasal
traditionally here.
SKYOB 'DOD say, SKYOB 'DOD.
It's really SKYOB 'DOD,
but there's a tradition to
pronounce it SKYOB 'DOD.
And SKYOB 'DOD means you want to %BSKYAB.
You want to protect that person.
So there's a slight difference in accent.
The first one just wants to
pull them out of the fire.
The second one is jump in
front of the fire and, yeah,
protect them from the fire.
It's a slight difference.
First one you don't have to
be a bodhisattva to have it.
The second one leads to
having bodhisattva vision,
bodhichitta.
So if you have this
big desire to wrap them
in your arms, in addition to
throwing them out of that fire
and you want to protect
them from the fire,
and presumably, even at your own expense,
maybe you take some of the pain yourself.
That's a higher kind of compassion
and only the bodhisattva
track people have that.
THEG CHEN THUN MONG MA YIN PA
That's unique to the Greater Way.
PHYI MA 'DI BSKYED PAR BYED,
therefore we are working
to get to the second one,
he says. PHYI MA means the second one,
we're working on the second one.
DES NA, 'DI DAG SKYE DKA' YANG
Oh, I sent a picture of a, I
was thinking of an umbrella.
This idea of taking refuge or
this idea of taking shelter.
I think umbrellas are nice
metaphors for taking refuge.
It's raining and not only
do you want to pull your
own child out of the rain,
but you have an umbrella ready for them.
It's a different thing.
You're ready to keep them dry,
not just to get them out of the wet.
So that's bodhisattva motivation.
DES NA, 'DI DAG SKYE
DKA' YANG SKYE THABS LA
BRTZON PA CHEN PO BSKYED DE 'BAD DGOS
Look, the second one's harder
because it starts to shade
into taking responsibility
for these people if you have the umbrella.
So you can feel how he's
taking us to the next step
in developing bodhichitta.
He's saying you should
have your umbrella ready
and what's he going to say next?
Then you should LHAG BSAM
Then you should take responsibility.
I carried an umbrella
around in my backpack.
Okay, why is that backpack so heavy?
I have an umbrella in there, I used to.
I carried it around for years in Arizona.
It doesn't rain in Arizona.
And then we went to see
the people at Google
to talk about Tibetan
translation and it poured,
and I pulled it out and I said, yay!
Scott and Orit were with
me and we all were--
Scott was not so dry but
me and Orit were dry.
But you know, you're ready.
All right.
SNGAR RANG NYID NA MYONG BA'I
NA MYONG BA
means if you have
experienced a certain kind of
disease, illness,
NAD DRAG PO if you've
had a serious illness,
like when I was studying in India,
I got what do you call it?
Hepatitis, yeah.
I was in bed for a month
and I couldn't get out of bed for a month.
And I recovered. There
is a Tibetan medicine,
by the way, and I recovered fine.
But after that I had a
special place in my heart
for people who got hepatitis.
So every time I heard
somebody got hepatitis,
I'm like yeah, I know,
man, I've been there.
You know, I had that.
I know how you feel to
lay in bed for a month.
I know how you feel.
So there's a kind of super empathy.
He says here, NA MYONG BA'I NAD DRAG PO
If you have experienced a
serious illness yourself,
DE 'DRA ZHIG MI GZHAN NA BA MTHONG NA
if you see another person
with that same disease,
RANG NYID KYI MYONG BA
RGYU MTSAN DU BYAS NAS
taking your previous personal
experience as a foundation,
SNYING RJE SKYE, you're
able to get compassion.
If you can relate to
something you had before
you're more compassionate towards people
who have the same disease.
SKYES BU CHUNG 'BRING GI SKABS
SU 'KHOR BA DANG NGAN SONG GI
SDUG BSNGAL RANG STENG DU
LEGS PAR BSGOMS PA RNAMS
Therefore, if you have
done the first ten years
of the Lam Rim well, and during the
person of lesser capacity
and the person of medium capacity steps,
you worked hard on
understanding all the suffering
you've had in your many lifetimes,
it's going to be easier
for you to have compassion
because you're already thinking
about all the times
you had those diseases.
So therefore, people who
get to the bodhisattva...
Why don't we start Lam Rim
at the bodhisattva section
of the Lam Rim is because first
you have to get sick yourself.
First, you have to go through
that disease yourself.
You have to be aware,
sensitive, to how you have had
all those problems yourself
in the lower realms,
with your previous marriages,
et cetera, et cetera.
If you've been through
all those sufferings
then you reach the bodhisattva
section of the Lam Rim,
you're ready to say,
Oh, I had that before.
I had that disease before.
I had the same thing with my ex-wife.
Yeah I understand,
or ex-husband.
And in that sense, studying the Lam Rim
is like laying bricks.
Studying the Lam Rim is very similar
to laying courses of bricks.
You can see here,
those lower levels of brick,
where the cement has dried already,
that's the steps of the path
for people of lesser capacity
and steps of the path for
people of medium capacity,
where we thought a lot
about our own troubles.
And that's like having hepatitis before.
Then when you reach this new
level that he's building now,
or she, and you're building
the bodhisattva levels
of the Lam Rim,
because you did a good
job in the medium level
of the Lam Rim and the
lesser levels of the Lam Rim,
your bodhisattva house is
going to be much stronger.
Now we talked about two
kinds of compassion.
He divided compassion into
sort of a lower compassion,
where you just want to
pull people out of the fire
and then a higher kind of
compassion where you want
to kind of hug them and protect them
from the fire and pull them out.
And now we're going to
get a similar distinction
in BYAMS PA, in love.
So there's two kinds of love,
which are kind of parallel
to those two kinds of compassion.
And again, it's not just BS,
a new category for the text
or something like that.
It's if you go deeper,
your experience of love and
compassion can go deeper.
So here we go.
SEMS CAN LA GCES SHING PHANGS
PA'I YID 'ONG GI BYAMS PA
We talked about beautiful love,
where you feel attracted to people.
When you're around people, you feel like
someone just gave you a
hundred thousand dollars
or something.
Every time a new person walks in the room
with all their bags of
troubles, you're like, oh wow,
here's another one I can practice with
and you feel like someone just
gave you a bag of diamonds
or something.
Like, wow, here's a new messed
up person I can be with.
And I'm so lucky.
So that's called GCES SHING PHANGS
GCES SHING PHANGS means the
person walks in the room
with their bag of troubles
and you feel hungry
to meet a new person that you can love.
It's kind of cool.
That's the first one.
Second one, BDE BA DANG
LDAN 'DOD KYI BYAMS PA GNYIS
That's where the person walks in the room
with all their troubles,
you feel attracted to them
and you want to give them something.
Like that additional detail
is you want to share something
with them or you want
to make them happier.
You feel like you want to
give them some cool new thing.
BYAMS PA GNYIS BYAMS PAR MTSUNGS
BYAMS PAR MTSUNGS means, they're
both love, both are love.
First one, where you just
see them as beautiful.
Second, where you have
this overwhelming desire
to give them something.
Okay, they're both love, I know.
KYANG but SPYI BYE BRAG LTA
BU'I KHYAD PAR CUNG ZAD YOD
There's a little bit of
SPYI BYE BRAG going on here.
Wow, what's that?
What's SPYI BYE BRAG in a general sense?
Here's a colloquial use
of SPYI BYE BRAG, which you
can use later for emptiness.
What is SPYI?
General and then BYE BRAG is?
(unclear)
Yeah, SPYI is like cars,
and BYE BRAG is like Tesla.
Which one of these two loves is the cars
and which one of these
two loves is the Tesla?
Don't forget, the first one was the person
comes in the room and you are already
strongly attracted to them
because you can help them.
And then in the second one,
you're dying to give them something.
Say again.
[Student] It is cars.
[GMR] Yeah, good, yeah.
Them coming in the room is SPYI, is cars.
And then the additional feature
that you want to give them something
is like BYE BRAG.
That's a specialized
form of the general love.
CUNG ZAD YOD means there's
a bit of a flavor that way.
It says, yeah, there's a
little flavor that way.
If you can catch it,
you can go deeper in your study of love.
And I would say, if you can
be sensitive to the parallel
in the two kinds of
compassion, that's very useful.
YID 'ONG GI BYAMS PA NI MAR SHES DRIN DRAN
DRIN GZO GSUM GYIS DRANGS SHING
When we talk about beautiful love,
which means when someone comes in the room
and needs something, it seems
extremely attractive to you.
When we talk about that kind of love
we're talking about the
love which was an automatic
result of MAR SHES DRIN DRAN DRIN GZO.
This has been my mom, she did this for me.
I want to pay her back.
Then that should trigger the
first kind of the general love,
SPYI love, where you're
attracted to the person.
What about the BYE BRAG kind?
DES SNYING RJE CHEN PO SKYED
PAR BYED PAS SNYING RJE
CHEN PO'I SNGON DU NGES PAR 'GRO DGOS
And by the way that general
love, where you feel attracted
to people is the one that you need
to get to step number five.
That supposedly triggers compassion
as one of the seven steps
in developing bodhichitta.
So in the scheme of the seven steps,
the first kind of love,
the general kind of love,
is important as a intermediate
step in the process.
So what about the other kind of love?
What was the other kind of love?
You want to
give them something.
BDE BA DANG PHRAD 'DOD KYI BYAMS PA
This is called
I-want-them-to-bump-into-happiness love.
PHRAD means bump into.
It's a cute name.
It means you want to give them something.
BDE BA DANG PHRAD 'DOD KYI BYAMS PA
DANG SNYING RJE LA RGYU 'BRAS GO RIM
Now think about it. He says
general love, where you
find people to be beautiful
because they need you,
that always triggers
compassion, where you want
to pull them out of the fire.
But,
that relationship between
compassion and the love
which wants to give something
to people can go both ways.
That's his point.
It could be that wanting
to give them something
leads you to want to
get them out of trouble,
or it could be they're wanting
to get them out of trouble
leads you to want to give them something.
And he says, that's the difference
and it's a little subtle.
And I got to say, it's such a pleasure,
I mean, how many places in the world,
how many rooms in the world right now
are people discussing,
which compassion came first
or the love came first, and
which kind of love came first
and which kind of comparison came before,
which kind of love?
I say, boy, we are so
lucky to be in a room
where someone is debating
how to love people better.
I'm saying to study Lam Rim,
to live with the scriptures,
is a beautiful life.
It's an extraordinarily beautiful life.
We're not talking about
which democrat you're going
to vote for, or republican.
We're not talking about
which Netflix film is better.
We're talking about, what kind of love
should I try to get first, Geshe-la?
I heard this one might be better
but I'm thinking the other one might.
Just to have the discussion is an honor.
LAM RIM CHEN MOR DRIN GZO'I
MJUG THOGS DER BDE BA DANG
PHRAD 'DOD KYI BYAMS PA
BSGOM TSUL GSUNGS PA LTAR
In the great Lam Rim of Tsongkapa
DRIN GZO'I MJUG THOGS DER
after you
practice wanting to pay back your mom,
you should go straight to the kind of love
where you want to give them something.
That's the Lam Rim.
That's Tsongkapa's position.
BSGOM TSUL GSUNGS PA
LTAR 'GA' ZHIG LA DE LTAR
SNYING RJE'I SNGON DU
BSGOM NA'ANG RUNG MOD
He says yeah, but some people say
you could switch the order.
You could do compassion first.
If you don't get a person out of trouble,
how can they enjoy the
candy you give them?
So there's a difference in the loves.
I like this picture of...
I always found it was easier
to think about it this way.
There's a school of
Buddhist thought that says,
come on,
if the kid falls down off the bicycle
and cuts their arm,
your first job is to put
something on the arm.
Then your second job is to
give them a piece of candy.
Don't give them a piece of candy
before you fix their
cut. Fix the cut first,
then give them the candy.
Compassion should come before love,
especially the love that
wants to give candy.
SKYONG TSUL MAN NGAG LUGS
LTAR BYED NA BDE BA DANG
PHRAD 'DOD KYI BYAMS PA
SNYING RJE'I RJES SU BSGOM
SKYONG TSUL MAN NGAG LUGS LTAR
means there's a oral tradition
and he's going to contradict
the LAM RIM CHEN MO,
the big Lam Rim.
He's going to say, look,
there's a tradition that
BDE BA DANG PHRAD 'DOD
KYI BYAMS PA SNYING RJE'I
RJES SU BSGOM
First, do the compassion
and then do the love
where you want to give them something.
You can do it this way.
DE NAS LHAG BSAM LA 'JUG PA YIN PAS
That will take you naturally
into taking responsibility for them.
DE LTAR NA BDE BA DANG LDAN
'DOD KYI BYAMS PA GTZO BOR
MTSAMS 'DIR BSGOM ZHING
Therefore, my recommendation,
Pabongka Rinpoche,
let's focus in this section,
on the kind of love where you want
to give something to them,
you want to share something with them,
because that's a good one
to go into responsibility.
LAM RIM CHEN MO'I SA BCAD
LTAR, SNYING RJE'I SNGON DU'ANG
YID 'ONG GI BYAMS PA
DANG SBRAGS NAS CUNG ZAD
BSAM DGOS GSUNGS,
But he said, if you want to
do it like the big Lam Rim,
like Tsongkapa's Lam Rim,
SNYING RJE'I SNGON DU'ANG
you could do love before compassion,
or SBRAGS NAS means you
could kind of combine them
at the same time.
And that would be okay.
SBRAGS means combine.
CUNG ZAD BSAM DGOS
You guys think about it, he
said. You guys think about it.
Think about it a bit.
It means it will be
profitable for you spiritually
if you figure this out yourself.
Should you worry first
about the pain people have
and then worry about their happiness?
Or should do you worry
about their happiness first
and then think about their pain?
Or is there some way you can mix it up?
Probably everything is
profitable spiritually.
LHAG BSAM, we're on to number six.
The six of the seven steps to
reaching this bodhisattva vision.
Step number one: see that
they have been your mother.
Number two: think about
all the good stuff they did for you.
Number three: think
about paying them back.
Number four: have love for them.
Number five: have compassion for them.
And now LHAG BSAM, which
means you take responsibility.
There's an American president,
Harry Truman, 1950 something,
and he had a sign on his desk
that said the buck stops here.
And that sign is very famous.
It means all the problems come to me
and I don't pass them on.
They have to be decided here.
I'm the last one in the line.
I'm the president.
Problems come up, come up,
come up through the government.
Then they reach here,
and then I understand
I have responsibility.
I'm the last person who
has to make decisions.
And he said,
I accept the responsibility.
I take, I understand,
I understand all the serious problems
will reach this office
and then they can't go out
of this office to somebody else.
I have to choose.
I have to make decisions, hard decisions.
DRUG PA LHAG BSAM NI, MA'I
KHUR BU LA BABS PA BZHIN
Look in the end, if someone gave you birth
and brought you up, then the
problem of taking care of them
is yours.
And this is famous with every generation
of humans that ever lived.
We all have to think
who's going to take care of
my mom when she gets old?
And in the end, there's
one person. It's you.
Why?
Because she's your mom, okay?
So pretty simple but
still a lot of Americans
have trouble with it.
BABS PA BZHIN, SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYI
I have a diamond dealer,
close spiritual friend
in India, and he built
a room for his father
onto his apartment,
and he wiped his father's
bottom for many years.
The father was senile.
He would sit there in the bed
and my friend would wash him every night,
clean up his poo poo every night.
And they live like that for years
and they built that
special room just for him.
LHAG BSAM NI, MA'I KHUR
BU LA BABS PA BZHIN
KHUR means the burden of
taking care of the mom
always should fall to the children.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYI
SDUG BSNGAL SEL BA DANG,
BDE BA THAMS CAD SGRUB
PA'I KHUR RANG GIS KHYER
Therefore, the responsibility
for everyone's happiness
and to stop everyone's
pain has fallen to us
because we're kids and
they're our mom. Don't forget.
So don't try to avoid your
natural responsibility.
KHUR RANG GIS KHYER NAS
SANGS RGYAS KYI SA LA BDAG
RANG GIS 'GOD
Therefore I will drag
myself to enlightenment.
Building the extra room
onto your apartment
means how to take care of your mom.
I got to get to enlightenment first
and then I'll be capable
to take care of my mom.
That's how you take care of your mom.
Don't focus on feeding
and cleaning your mom.
Focus on getting to enlightenment
and then you can really
take care of your mom.
It doesn't mean you don't
have to clean your mom,
but it means in the end
your motivation should be,
I want to get to Buddhahood
so I can really help my
mom because that's my duty.
That's my natural duty.
RANG GIS 'GOD CES THAG BCAD PA NI
THAG BCAD PA NI
means make up your mind.
Like, stop being wishy-washy,
make up your mind.
Look, we've been going
through all these steps
for bodhichitta. Just decide.
Yeah, those are my mom. - Okay.
So you got to take care of her. - How?
You got and get to Buddhahood
as fast as you can.
That's the son and
daughter's responsibility.
NYAN RANG LAS LHAG PA'I BSAM PA STE
And then he explains LHAG BSAM
which is very interesting.
I looked up the Sanskrit is adhyashaya,
adhyashaya,
which means to have a superior thought.
LHAG PA here like LHAG
MTHONG, vipashyana, it means a
higher level of thinking
is adhyashaya, LHAG BSAM.
And then he makes a joke,
Pabongka Rinpoche says,
LHAG than who? Adhi than who?
It's supposed to be,
it's supposed to be a higher
kind of thinking process.
Higher than who? Xan you guess?
For $50?
Higher than the two
lower tracks.
$50 for Tim.
Jigme,
$50 for Mr. Tim.
Oh no, that's your job.
They'll cheat us.
They'll say they didn't make it.
Yeah.
He got $25 for self-made buddhas
and $25 for listeners.
So LHAG BSAM LHAG PA'I BSAM PA STE,
So he explained the LHAG in LHAG BSAM,
which means
special responsibility
and what it means is
more special than a
non-bodhisattva practitioners.
And you won't see LHAG BSAM
ever explained like that.
And you have to be
sensitive that he's doing it
because he doesn't announce it.
All right.
I like to call it the
majesty of responsibility.
I have a picture.
Okay Geshe-la, what the heck?
I mean this is supposed to be some person
taking responsibility
for a whole civilization
and you got a lady throwing
a bottle in a garbage can.
Yeah. Why?
She took responsibility for the planet
in a small, personal way.
I used to drink a lot of fizzy water
in from, what's that place, Fiji,
and my friend Pachi
said, Geshe-la come on,
that's lame.
You're stealing water
out of this tiny island
and shipping in a jet
airplane through the sky,
burning fuel the whole way
to get it to you in Sedona.
Come on.
So this lady took responsibility
and she didn't ask anybody.
She didn't announce it to anybody.
I liked to think that she picked up
a plastic bottle on the street
and she put it in the garbage can.
And that's called
glorious majesty of responsibility.
She is a queen at that moment.
She's more queen than those
guys running around in London.
She's more of a queen.
She's throwing out the plastic bottle.
She bent over and picked
up the plastic bottle
and put it in the garbage because
she's taking quietly, anonymously,
she's taking responsibility.
DPER NA, MI ZHIG G-YANG
DU LHUNG BA MTHONG BA
MA BZOD NAS DE 'DON
MKHAN BYUNG NA CI MA RUNG
means if you see somebody fall off a ship
into the Pacific Ocean
and you're at the rail,
you know like Titanic.
And you're like, oh I
hope someone grabs him.
I hope someone can get to him.
You know, like, oh,
I hope so bad that someone saves him.
Or what's going to happen next?
You jump.
RUNG SNYAM PA LTA BU NI
BYAMS PA SNYING RJE GNYIS
DANG MTSUNGS SHING
That is kind of love and
that is kind of compassion.
But DE LTAR MA BZHAG PAR RANG
GIS 'DON RGYUR BLO THAG BCAD
BLO THAG BCAD
means make the god damned decision.
Somebody has to jump off the
Titanic and grab this person.
It's going to be me.
That's called THAG BCAD PA
It's a beautiful verb in Tibetan.
It means the buck stops here.
I'm not going to look to somebody else.
Oh, somebody fell off the boat.
You have to find a staff
person to try to help them.
No - THAG BCAD PA
means you don't talk to anybody,
just god damn take off your
shirt and jump in the water
and go after them.
That's THAG BCAD PA.
LHAG BSAM DANG 'DRA BAS,
that's personal responsibility.
SPYIR BYAMS PA DANG SNYING RJE
TZAM NYAN RANG LA YOD KYANG
Generally speaking,
non-bodhisattvas can have feelings
of compassion and love for other people,
but, KYANG, LHAG BSAM, no,
they don't have it.
They are not going to say,
I'm the person who's jumping off the ship.
Unless you're on the bodhisattva track,
you're going to look
around for a staff member
and let them know somebody
fell out the boat.
If you're on the bodhisattva track,
you're going to LHAG BSAM.
You're going to say, oh wow, so cool,
it came down to me. I'm the one.
I got to, I got to jump now.
So, all right, and we've all
been in those situations.
If you get to my age,
you been in situations
where you have to make a quick decision.
Either I risk my life or
I wait for somebody else.
And then you just,
it's nice if you have this,
if you're able to feel LHAG BSAM
and say, okay, it's
down to me, let's do it.
It's a very beautiful thing.
You feel very proud of yourself later
that you didn't look for a staff person.
I'm telling you it's one
of the pleasures of life.
LHAG BSAM 'DI DANG DRIN GZO'I
SKABS KYI KHUR KHYER LUGS
So somebody asks a question
to Pabongka Rinpoche.
You're talking about taking
responsibility, right?
- Yeah.
How does that differ from the third step?
Where you want to
DRIN GZO, pay them back.
What's the difference
between step number six
and step number three?
Well, step number three
is I'll pay my mom back.
She took care of me, I'll pay her back.
And what's the difference between that
and step number six,
where you say it's on me?
He says, you tell me the difference.
Here he answers
DPER NA TSONG PAS NOR RDZAS
NYO BAR BRTZOM PA DANG
You are in tje department store,
you see a beautiful dress,
and you're like, man.
I remember I was in Taiwan.
I went to Christian Dior.
They had a $3,000, sorry,
they had a nice dress
and I thought I'm going
to buy that for Veronica.
I stood there for like 20 minutes
and I said, "God that's one
of the most beautiful dresses
I ever seen."
And then I asked the lady,
how much is the dress?
And she said $3,000 or $5,000
and I'm like [drops jaw].
And then you have this moment,
are you going to jump on not?
By the way, I did not,
but maybe I should have.
But I thought it was too much.
But in that moment you
have a decision to make.
Are you going to jump or not?
So, normal compassion,
normal love,
is like admiring the dress.
And then the difference
between that and LHAG BSAM,
the difference between that
and taking responsibility is?
Yeah, here's the credit card, god damn.
Here's the god damn credit card.
By the way, I didn't do it.
I mean, I did it in another place and
she ended up giving the
dress to Peter and Marija
for her wedding because
it was so beautiful.
She said, there is a
wedding dress, Geshe-la.
And anyway,
it's an interesting
distinction for Pabongka,
who's not supposed to
be engaged in business.
We read that in the monk's vows
last term in the Mixed Nuts.
He's like, it's like when you take out
your god damn credit card,
put it down on the counter.
I'm up for it . I'm there.
Here's my credit card.
Okay, so think about it.
It's an interesting
analogy for a monk to make.
TSONG THAG BCAD PA
means you decide.
BZHIN GYI BLO THAG BCAD PA
means you make that decision.
You jump. You jump.
MA BCAD PA'I KHYAD PAR YIN
If you don't jump yet,
that's number three.
I would like to pay her back.
And if you do jump it's number six.
I'm going to pay her back.
Got it? Cool?
ZHES BLA MA RIN PO CHE GSUNG
BLA MA RIN PO CHE GSUNG means
my teacher taught me that,
said our teacher.
So he's crediting it to,
what's his teacher's name?
Who wrote the...
SBYOR LAM
SBYOR CHOS, he wrote the SBYOR CHOS.
Anyway, you can check.
I always forget his name,
Pabongka Rinpoche's teacher.
He said that's what my teacher said.
Oh so maybe his teacher was buying horses
and stuff, I don't know.
And I like the picture here,
this guy's calling his mom,
"Okay, I bought my first building,
like I jumped, you know, I
signed the mortgage just now."
The building's behind him.
I remember when we bought our
first building in New York
and it was a big gamble.
It was a big risk.
We waffled for a couple months
and then we said, god damn let's do it,
and that feeling in your heart like,
okay, god damn, I'm there,
I'm going to buy it.
I think that he's like
that guy in New York, 1990-something,
who said, okay, mom,
I bought the building.
I made the decision.
For better or for worse.
All right.
That finishes up LHAG BSAM.
Ad we're on the border
of step number seven, which
is what does it feel like
to really have that vision
to jump between planets, taking
care of billions of people?
And we're going to pick that up
in the next Lam Rim course.
Yay!
Thank you, and we're going
to have a small review,
one more class and we'll review
everything we've talked about
during these 14 classes.
Okay, see you then.